<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-04-22T17:25:33+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/</id><title type="html">Sigit Purwadi’s Blog</title><subtitle>You're nobody until you're talked about</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hello World v2</title><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/hello-world" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World v2" /><published>2017-07-27T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/hello-world">&lt;p&gt;I have been away from the blogging scene for quite a while now, suddenly today it dawned upon me that I need to start writing/posting again. My writing is a little bit rusty now, and I need to brush on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&quot;The beginning is the most important part of the work.&quot;
~ Plato&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, the moment I thought about blogging, Wordpress flashed in my mind. Well, I used Wordpress &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in the past and it worked well for a while, then I had to face issues like high-traffic and high CPU load and unexpected spikes in my server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those weren’t too much trouble, I would avoid fixing those bugs if I was busy, and sometimes I would leave the system untouched for 2 days straight and let the server admins frown and try to mitigate the outage. &lt;i&gt;I had a pretty straight forward deal with my hosting provider, that no matter what, they can’t shut down my website.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PHP runtime errors weren’t a big deal, the hundreds of thousands of SQL database queries weren’t a trouble, sometimes the site would run a tad bit slower than average, but it was OK overall for me. A sample of the emails I would receive from my hosting provider is given below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hello,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I apologize, but I was forced to suspend the script “/home/xxxxx/public_html/xxxxxx/index.php” as it was causing a high load on the server, and due to it affecting all of the other accounts on the system, I was forced to take immediate action for the health of the server.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I did notice that this was a Wordpress installation, and would recommend that you enable caching for it.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Please note that if you already have caching enabled, you will need to take more action such as looking into any high use modules or plugins, and seeing if there are any updates, or possibly any that you can disable to reduce the load that your site causes.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;If you reply back to this with your IP address we will be more than happy to go ahead enable HTTP access for you, so that you can safely work on the script without it causing further issues. Please let me know how you would like to proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the game was changed when my site got hacked. Wordpress is notorious in getting hacked. The PHP code libraries are huge, and while Automattic tries to keep it relatively clean and bug free, bugs do persist among the thousands of lines of codes and every once in a while a bug gets discovered by the code breakers. If the bug can be exploited in some way to gain access of the site, the code breakers tend to do some serious damage. While I wasn’t been exclusively targeted by such individuals, I was part of a victimized group who used the same version of Wordpress, and all of our sites got defaced by some mass defacing software. Although it didn’t do serious damage, as I have daily off-site backup, I became dubious about the Wordpress platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this time around, while I was still brainstorming for ideas and theme designs and what not, I decided to go back to Jekyll, or you may say, rather old school. Why not use plain static HTML files with some CSS styling and JS animations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Proudly present: The new &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/MNbxc6b6mF&quot;&gt;https://t.co/MNbxc6b6mF&lt;/a&gt; , a fast and flexible modern static blogsite built with love 💖&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sigit Purwadi H. W. (@S_Purwadi) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/S_Purwadi/status/677392010395836420&quot;&gt;December 17, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static sites are impossible to hack, as there are no codes needed to be run on the server. The only way a static site can be compromised if the code breakers have access to your FTP account. So I used Jekyll and GIT Version Control to do that for me. And it was so efficient that I would post materials daily instead of weekly. It was like love on first use. But Wordpress had lots of theme choices and for my personal site I decided to use Wordpress anyways disregarding the simpleness and speed static sites provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the takeover of my Wordpress powered blog happened, I turned to self written PHP sites and static sites completely. I have built a social network based on PHP for my peer group which is highly secure but when it comes down to speed it lags behind. So I built this site using Jekyll, a blog aware static site generator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this site will perform as envisioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This domain previously hosted a Wordpress blog.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>&amp;#64;S_Purwadi</name></author><category term="artcytech" /><summary type="html">I have been away from the blogging scene for quite a while now, suddenly today it dawned upon me that I need to start writing/posting again. My writing is a little bit rusty now, and I need to brush on that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Ghost</title><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/welcome" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Ghost" /><published>2017-07-27T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/welcome">&lt;p&gt;Hey! Welcome to Ghost, it’s great to have you :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that first impressions are important, so we’ve populated your new site with some initial &lt;strong&gt;Getting Started&lt;/strong&gt; posts that will help you get familiar with everything in no time. This is the first one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;there-are-a-few-things-that-you-should-know-up-front&quot;&gt;There are a few things that you should know up-front:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ghost is designed for ambitious, professional publishers who want to actively build a business around their content. That’s who it works best for. If you’re using Ghost for some other purpose, that’s fine too - but it might not be the best choice for you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The entire platform can be modified and customized to suit your needs, which is very powerful, but doing so &lt;strong&gt;does&lt;/strong&gt; require some knowledge of code. Ghost is not necessarily a good platform for beginners or people who just want a simple personal blog.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the best experience we recommend downloading the Ghost Desktop App for your computer, which is the best way to access your Ghost site on a desktop device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost is made by an independent non-profit organisation called the Ghost Foundation. We are 100% self funded by revenue from our &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghost.org/pricing&quot;&gt;Ghost(Pro)&lt;/a&gt; service, and every penny we make is re-invested into funding further development of free, open source technology for modern journalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing you’ll want to read about next is probably: &lt;a href=&quot;https://demo.ghost.io/the-editor/&quot;&gt;the Ghost editor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’re done reading, you can simply delete the default &lt;strong&gt;Ghost&lt;/strong&gt; user from your team to remove all of these introductory posts!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>&amp;#64;S_Purwadi</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">Hey! Welcome to Ghost, it’s great to have you :)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hal-Hal yang (Sebenarnya) Tidak Penting Ketika Sekolah</title><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/hal-yang-sebenarnya-tidak-penting-ketika-sekolah" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hal-Hal yang (Sebenarnya) Tidak Penting Ketika Sekolah" /><published>2017-07-27T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/hal-yang-sebenarnya-tidak-penting-ketika-sekolah</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/hal-yang-sebenarnya-tidak-penting-ketika-sekolah">&lt;p&gt;Halloo, wahai jiwa-jiwa yang masih diikat oleh bel istirahat…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apa kabar buku dan pensil kalian?
Apa kabar keadaan kelas kalian?
Bagaimana kabar tentang para pencinta teman sekelas, tapi sampe sekarang masih takut buat nyatain perasaan??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Itu 3 nomor yang tadi ntar dicatat yah, minggu depan dikumpul. Khusus untuk pertanyaan terakhir bisa dikumpul ntar kalo udah lulus sekolah. :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Menurut gue, selama kita sekolah kurang lebih 12 tahun, banyak sekali hal-hal yang sebenarnya tidak penting yang diajarkan ketika kita sekolah. &lt;strong&gt;Kita dididik selama 12 tahun untuk mengerjakan hal yang sama&lt;/strong&gt;, tapi hasilnya?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hanya sedikit orang yang bisa mengambil hikmah dari masa sekolah dulu, sisanya? Tau entah ilmunya kabur kemana… Langsung saja kita ke beberapa hal-hal yang sebenarnya tidak penting yang diajarkan ketika sekolah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-cabut-rumput&quot;&gt;1. Cabut Rumput&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-qfiVBIbauII/VTJGxBi4-OI/AAAAAAAAAgM/ivy23iBNPbE/s1600/CIMG7075.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Cabut rumput&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kegiatan kayak gini biasanya sih dilakuin di pagi hari ketika hari Jum’at. &lt;del&gt;Hukuman&lt;/del&gt; cabut rumput ini biasa juga berlaku bagi mereka yang suka terlambat. Kita biasanya &lt;del&gt;dipaksa&lt;/del&gt; disuruh untuk mencabut rumput-rumput yang sudah tumbuh kayak &lt;del&gt;bulu ketek bulu idung rambut kaki&lt;/del&gt; sapu ijuk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entah apa makna dari semua ini, tapi dari kabar yang gue dengar, katanya kegiatan ini diadakan agar kita belajar mencintai lingkungan dan menghargai alam. PRET!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kalo kita didik selama 12 tahun untuk mencintai lingkungan dan menghargai alam, kenapa masih banyak dari kita yang hobi membuang sampah di laut? Kenapa masih banyak dari kita yang suka menebang pohon sembarangan? Atau jangan-jangan, faktor terbesar ‘&lt;em&gt;penggundulan&lt;/em&gt;’ hutan secara ilegal mungkin karena kita sering mengikuti kegiatan &lt;strong&gt;cabut rumput&lt;/strong&gt; yang diadakan tiap hari jumat pagi, makanya banyak dari kita yang sudah memvonis bahwa semua tumbuhan yang berwarna hijau itu adalah rumput, maka dari itu semua pohon “&lt;em&gt;dicabut&lt;/em&gt;” secara ilegal demi mencintai lingkungan dan menghargai alam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-ujian-bahasa-indonesia&quot;&gt;2. Ujian Bahasa Indonesia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://musikgelombangotak.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/terapi-penghilang-ngantuk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tidur..&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pernah belajar mata pelajaran bahasa Indonesia kan?
Menurut gue, ini pelajaran yang amat sangat penting bagi kita. Masa iya kita tinggal di Indonesia tapi kita sendiri nggak ngerti bahasa Indonesia? Ini kan lucu namanya…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terlepas dari itu semua, menurut gue ada hal yang nggak penting yang diajarkan disini. Pernah ikut ujian bahasa Indonesia kan? Pernah gak ketemu soal ujian bahasa Indonesia yang soalnya cuman 1 atau 2 lembar? Pasti gak bakalan ketemu! Kalo pun ketemu, itu berarti soal-soal yang dibuat untuk mereka yang belum akil baligh…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nah sekarang pertanyaannya adalah, “&lt;em&gt;Apa sih manfaatnya bikin soal sebanyak itu?&lt;/em&gt;”. Bikin soal sebanyak itu cuman bikin waktu dan tenaga kita terbuang sia-sia saja, ujung-ujungnya cuman buat bikin ngantuk ketika ujian dan nggak bakalan ada manfaatnya. Mau bukti? Tuh, liat di sosial media sana, masih banyak orang-orang yang belum bisa menulis status dengan baik dan benar. Mereka hobi menggabungkan huruf dengan angka. Mungkin selama sekolah, mereka ini hobi dengan pelajaran matematika, kimia atau fisika. mungkin?? iya.. &lt;del&gt;tidak&lt;/del&gt;, bisa jadi..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kedepannya sih gue harap lembar-lembar soal untuk ujian bahasa indonesia nggak setebal &lt;del&gt;kikil kulit sapi&lt;/del&gt; buku telepon…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buat para guru yang bingung mau nyusun soal, nih gue kasih tips supaya soalnya nggak tebal lagi kayak dulu…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cobalah memberikan soal yang pendek tapi menggunakan bahasa Indonesia yang baik.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gunakanlah pilihan ganda yang mudah dipahami oleh para siswa. Gue kasih contohnya biar lengkap…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;contoh:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ketika Ipang lapar, ia seharusnya…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A. Makan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;B. Update Status&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C. Update Status&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D. Update Status&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;E. Update Status&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bagaimanakah cara menulis kalimat “&lt;em&gt;Selamat Siang&lt;/em&gt;” yang baik dan benar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A. sElAmAT SiANG&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;B. s3L4M4T 514176&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C. Zelamadh  Ziank&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D. Selamat Siang&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;E. Ceyamat Cyank^^&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gue yakin ketika semua guru menggunakan soal-soal seperti ini, akan banyak siswa yang nantinya bakalan hebat berbahasa Indonesia dan jauh dari siksaan api neraka. Amiin…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-bangun-pagi&quot;&gt;3. Bangun Pagi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.youthmanual.com/assets/file_uploaded/editor/1459849119-2012-03-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ngantuk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kegiatan ini yang sebenarnya paling gue benci ketika sekolah. Kita diwajibkan untuk bangun pagi-pagi dan berangkat ke sekolah. Gue nggak ngerti apa sebenarnya maksud dari “mereka”, sang pembuat peraturan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katanya, mereka membangun sistem “&lt;em&gt;bangun dan berangkat ke sekolah pagi-pagi&lt;/em&gt;” dengan tujuan  untuk melatih sikap kedisiplinan kita. Untuk kesekian kalinya saya bertanya, &lt;strong&gt;MANA BUKTINYA??&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bukankah mereka yang sekarang kerjaannya duduk dibawah AC “&lt;em&gt;diatas&lt;/em&gt;” sana dulu juga pernah bangun dan berangkat ke sekolah pagi-pagi? Tapi mana kedisiplinan mereka? Ketika rapat malah tidur, datang sering terlambat, kadang juga bolos, dan lebih parahnya lagi, suka nonton maap &lt;del&gt;b**ep&lt;/del&gt;  ketika sedang kerja. Inikah yang mereka sebut kedisiplinan ? Wah-wah, ternyata parah sekali tingkat kedisiplinan negara kita ini yah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ya sudah, segitu dulu kayaknya postingan gue kali ini… Mudah-mudahan 3 dari sekian banyak hal seperti ini dihilangan atau setidaknya sistemnya dirubah. Bosan lama-lama dengan sistem yang nggak bisa menghasilkan manfaat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kalo ada lagi yang ingin ngasih tau hal-hal apa lagi yang ingin dihilangkan ketika sekolah lagi karena nggak penting lagi, silahkan komen di box komentar yang ada dibawah..&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>&amp;#64;S_Purwadi</name></author><category term="education" /><summary type="html">Halloo, wahai jiwa-jiwa yang masih diikat oleh bel istirahat…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Using the Ghost editor</title><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/the-editor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using the Ghost editor" /><published>2017-07-27T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/the-editor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/the-editor">&lt;p&gt;Ghost uses a language called &lt;strong&gt;Markdown&lt;/strong&gt; to format text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you go to edit a post and see special characters and colours intertwined between the words, those are Markdown shortcuts which tell Ghost what to do with the words in your document. The biggest benefit of Markdown is that you can quickly apply formatting as you type, without needing to pause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the bottom of the editor, you'll find a toolbar with basic formatting options to help you get started as easily as possible. You'll also notice that there's a &lt;strong&gt;?&lt;/strong&gt; icon, which contains more advanced shortcuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, though, let's run you through some of the basics. You'll want to make sure you're editing this post in order to see all the Markdown we've used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;formattingtext&quot;&gt;Formatting text&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common shortcuts are of course, &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt; text, &lt;em&gt;italic&lt;/em&gt; text, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://example.com&quot;&gt;hyperlinks&lt;/a&gt;. These generally make up the bulk of any document. You can type the characters out, but you can also use keyboard shortcuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;CMD/Ctrl + B&lt;/code&gt; for Bold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;CMD/Ctrl + I&lt;/code&gt; for Italic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;CMD/Ctrl + K&lt;/code&gt; for a Link&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;CMD/Ctrl + H&lt;/code&gt; for a Heading (Press multiple times for h2/h3/h4/etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With just a couple of extra characters here and there, you're well on your way to creating a beautifully formatted story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;insertingimages&quot;&gt;Inserting images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images in Markdown look just the same as links, except they're prefixed with an exclamation mark, like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;![Image description](/path/to/image.jpg)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://casper.ghost.org/v1.0.0/images/computer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Computer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most Markdown editors don't make you type this out, though. In Ghost you can click on the image icon in the toolbar at the bottom of the editor, or you can just click and drag an image from your desktop directly into the editor. Both will upload the image for you and generate the appropriate Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Ghost does not currently have automatic image resizing, so it's always a good idea to make sure your images aren't gigantic files &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt; uploading them to Ghost.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;makinglists&quot;&gt;Making lists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists in HTML are a formatting nightmare, but in Markdown they become an absolute breeze with just a couple of characters and a bit of smart automation. For numbered lists, just write out the numbers. For bullet lists, just use &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt;. Like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crack the eggs over a bowl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whisk them together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make an omellete&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember to buy milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feed the cat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Come up with idea for next story&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;addingquotes&quot;&gt;Adding quotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you want to pull out a particularly good except in the middle of a piece, you can use &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; at the beginning of a paragraph to turn it into a Blockquote. You might've seen this formatting before in email clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A well placed quote guides a reader through a story, helping them to understand the most important points being made&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All themes handles blockquotes slightly differently. Sometimes they'll look better kept shorter, while other times you can quote fairly hefty amounts of text and get away with it. Generally, the safest option is to use blockquotes sparingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dividingthingsup&quot;&gt;Dividing things up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're writing a piece in parts and you just feel like you need to divide a couple of sections distinctly from each other, a horizontal rule might be just what you need. Dropping &lt;code&gt;---&lt;/code&gt; on a new line will create a sleak divider, anywhere you want it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should get you going with the vast majority of what you need to do in the editor, but if you're still curious about more advanced tips then check out the &lt;a href=&quot;/advanced-markdown/&quot;&gt;Advanced Markdown Guide&lt;/a&gt; - or if you'd rather learn about how Ghost taxononomies work, we've got a overview of &lt;a href=&quot;/using-tags/&quot;&gt;how to use Ghost tags&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>&amp;#64;S_Purwadi</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">Ghost uses a language called Markdown to format text. When you go to edit a post and see special characters and colours intertwined between the words, those are Markdown shortcuts which tell Ghost what to do with the words in your document. The biggest benefit of Markdown is that you can quickly apply formatting as you type, without needing to pause. At the bottom of the editor, you'll find a toolbar with basic formatting options to help you get started as easily as possible. You'll also notice that there's a ? icon, which contains more advanced shortcuts. For now, though, let's run you through some of the basics. You'll want to make sure you're editing this post in order to see all the Markdown we've used. Formatting text The most common shortcuts are of course, bold text, italic text, and hyperlinks. These generally make up the bulk of any document. You can type the characters out, but you can also use keyboard shortcuts. CMD/Ctrl + B for Bold CMD/Ctrl + I for Italic CMD/Ctrl + K for a Link CMD/Ctrl + H for a Heading (Press multiple times for h2/h3/h4/etc) With just a couple of extra characters here and there, you're well on your way to creating a beautifully formatted story. Inserting images Images in Markdown look just the same as links, except they're prefixed with an exclamation mark, like this: ![Image description](/path/to/image.jpg) Most Markdown editors don't make you type this out, though. In Ghost you can click on the image icon in the toolbar at the bottom of the editor, or you can just click and drag an image from your desktop directly into the editor. Both will upload the image for you and generate the appropriate Markdown. Important Note: Ghost does not currently have automatic image resizing, so it's always a good idea to make sure your images aren't gigantic files before uploading them to Ghost. Making lists Lists in HTML are a formatting nightmare, but in Markdown they become an absolute breeze with just a couple of characters and a bit of smart automation. For numbered lists, just write out the numbers. For bullet lists, just use * or - or +. Like this: Crack the eggs over a bowl Whisk them together Make an omellete or Remember to buy milk Feed the cat Come up with idea for next story Adding quotes When you want to pull out a particularly good except in the middle of a piece, you can use &amp;gt; at the beginning of a paragraph to turn it into a Blockquote. You might've seen this formatting before in email clients. A well placed quote guides a reader through a story, helping them to understand the most important points being made All themes handles blockquotes slightly differently. Sometimes they'll look better kept shorter, while other times you can quote fairly hefty amounts of text and get away with it. Generally, the safest option is to use blockquotes sparingly. Dividing things up If you're writing a piece in parts and you just feel like you need to divide a couple of sections distinctly from each other, a horizontal rule might be just what you need. Dropping --- on a new line will create a sleak divider, anywhere you want it. This should get you going with the vast majority of what you need to do in the editor, but if you're still curious about more advanced tips then check out the Advanced Markdown Guide - or if you'd rather learn about how Ghost taxononomies work, we've got a overview of how to use Ghost tags.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Organising your content with tags</title><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/using-tags" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Organising your content with tags" /><published>2017-07-27T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/using-tags</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/using-tags">&lt;p&gt;Ghost has a single, powerful organisational taxonomy, called tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter whether you want to call them categories, tags, boxes, or anything else. You can think of Ghost tags a lot like Gmail labels. By tagging posts with one or more keyword, you can organise articles into buckets of related content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;basictagging&quot;&gt;Basic tagging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you write a post, you can assign tags to help differentiate between categories of content. For example, you might tag some posts with &lt;code&gt;News&lt;/code&gt; and other posts with &lt;code&gt;Cycling&lt;/code&gt;, which would create two distinct categories of content listed on &lt;code&gt;/tag/news/&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;/tag/cycling/&lt;/code&gt;, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you tag a post with both &lt;code&gt;News&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;Cycling&lt;/code&gt; - then it appears in both sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tag archives are like dedicated home-pages for each category of content that you have. They have their own pages, their own RSS feeds, and can support their own cover images and meta data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;theprimarytag&quot;&gt;The primary tag&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the Ghost editor, you can drag and drop tags into a specific order. The first tag in the list is always given the most importance, and some themes will only display the primary tag (the first tag in the list) by default. So you can add the most important tag which you want to show up in your theme, but also add a bunch of related tags which are less important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;&lt;strong&gt;News&lt;/strong&gt;, Cycling, Bart Stevens, Extreme Sports&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example, &lt;strong&gt;News&lt;/strong&gt; is the primary tag which will be displayed by the theme, but the post will also still receive all the other tags, and show up in their respective archives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;privatetags&quot;&gt;Private tags&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you may want to assign a post a specific tag, but you don't necessarily want that tag appearing in the theme or creating an archive page. In Ghost, hashtags are private and can be used for special styling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you sometimes publish posts with video content - you might want your theme to adapt and get rid of the sidebar for these posts, to give more space for an embedded video to fill the screen. In this case, you could use private tags to tell your theme what to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;&lt;strong&gt;News&lt;/strong&gt;, Cycling, #video&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, the theme would assign the post publicly displayed tags of &lt;code&gt;News&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;Cycling&lt;/code&gt; - but it would also keep a private record of the post being tagged with &lt;code&gt;#video&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your theme, you could then look for private tags conditionally and give them special formatting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;nohighlight&quot;&gt;{{#post}}
    {{#has tag=&amp;quot;#video&amp;quot;}}
        ...markup for a nice big video post layout...
    {{else}}
        ...regular markup for a post...
    {{/has}}
{{/post}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find documentation for theme development techniques like this and many more over on Ghost's extensive &lt;a href=&quot;https://themes.ghost.org/&quot;&gt;theme documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>&amp;#64;S_Purwadi</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">Ghost has a single, powerful organisational taxonomy, called tags. It doesn't matter whether you want to call them categories, tags, boxes, or anything else. You can think of Ghost tags a lot like Gmail labels. By tagging posts with one or more keyword, you can organise articles into buckets of related content. Basic tagging When you write a post, you can assign tags to help differentiate between categories of content. For example, you might tag some posts with News and other posts with Cycling, which would create two distinct categories of content listed on /tag/news/ and /tag/cycling/, respectively. If you tag a post with both News and Cycling - then it appears in both sections. Tag archives are like dedicated home-pages for each category of content that you have. They have their own pages, their own RSS feeds, and can support their own cover images and meta data. The primary tag Inside the Ghost editor, you can drag and drop tags into a specific order. The first tag in the list is always given the most importance, and some themes will only display the primary tag (the first tag in the list) by default. So you can add the most important tag which you want to show up in your theme, but also add a bunch of related tags which are less important. News, Cycling, Bart Stevens, Extreme Sports In this example, News is the primary tag which will be displayed by the theme, but the post will also still receive all the other tags, and show up in their respective archives. Private tags Sometimes you may want to assign a post a specific tag, but you don't necessarily want that tag appearing in the theme or creating an archive page. In Ghost, hashtags are private and can be used for special styling. For example, if you sometimes publish posts with video content - you might want your theme to adapt and get rid of the sidebar for these posts, to give more space for an embedded video to fill the screen. In this case, you could use private tags to tell your theme what to do. News, Cycling, #video Here, the theme would assign the post publicly displayed tags of News, and Cycling - but it would also keep a private record of the post being tagged with #video. In your theme, you could then look for private tags conditionally and give them special formatting: {{#post}} {{#has tag=&amp;quot;#video&amp;quot;}} ...markup for a nice big video post layout... {{else}} ...regular markup for a post... {{/has}} {{/post}} You can find documentation for theme development techniques like this and many more over on Ghost's extensive theme documentation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Managing Ghost users</title><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/managing-users" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Managing Ghost users" /><published>2017-07-27T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/managing-users</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/managing-users">&lt;p&gt;Ghost has a number of different user roles for your team&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;authors&quot;&gt;Authors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The base user level in Ghost is an author. Authors can write posts, edit their own posts, and publish their own posts. Authors are &lt;strong&gt;trusted&lt;/strong&gt; users. If you don't trust users to be allowed to publish their own posts, you shouldn't invite them to Ghost admin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;editors&quot;&gt;Editors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Editors are the 2nd user level in Ghost. Editors can do everything that an Author can do, but they can also edit and publish the posts of others - as well as their own. Editors can also invite new authors to the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;administrators&quot;&gt;Administrators&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top user level in Ghost is Administrator. Again, administrators can do everything that Authors and Editors can do, but they can also edit all site settings and data, not just content. Additionally, administrators have full access to invite, manage or remove any other user of the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;theowner&quot;&gt;The Owner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is only ever one owner of a Ghost site. The owner is a special user which has all the same permissions as an Administrator, but with two exceptions: The Owner can never be deleted. And in some circumstances the owner will have access to additional special settings if applicable — for example, billing details, if using Ghost(Pro).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a good idea to ask all of your users to fill out their user profiles, including bio and social links. These will populate rich structured data for posts and generally create more opportunities for themes to fully populate their design.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>&amp;#64;S_Purwadi</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">Ghost has a number of different user roles for your team Authors The base user level in Ghost is an author. Authors can write posts, edit their own posts, and publish their own posts. Authors are trusted users. If you don't trust users to be allowed to publish their own posts, you shouldn't invite them to Ghost admin. Editors Editors are the 2nd user level in Ghost. Editors can do everything that an Author can do, but they can also edit and publish the posts of others - as well as their own. Editors can also invite new authors to the site. Administrators The top user level in Ghost is Administrator. Again, administrators can do everything that Authors and Editors can do, but they can also edit all site settings and data, not just content. Additionally, administrators have full access to invite, manage or remove any other user of the site. The Owner There is only ever one owner of a Ghost site. The owner is a special user which has all the same permissions as an Administrator, but with two exceptions: The Owner can never be deleted. And in some circumstances the owner will have access to additional special settings if applicable — for example, billing details, if using Ghost(Pro). It's a good idea to ask all of your users to fill out their user profiles, including bio and social links. These will populate rich structured data for posts and generally create more opportunities for themes to fully populate their design.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making your site private</title><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/private-sites" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making your site private" /><published>2017-07-27T06:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T06:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/private-sites</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/private-sites">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you might want to put your site behind closed doors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've got a publication that you don't want the world to see yet because it's not ready to launch, you can hide your Ghost site behind a simple shared pass-phrase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can toggle this preference on at the bottom of Ghost's General Settings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://casper.ghost.org/v1.0.0/images/private.png&quot; alt=&quot;private&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghost will give you a short, randomly generated pass-phrase which you can share with anyone who needs access to the site while you're working on it. While this setting is enabled, all search engine optimisation features will be switched off to help keep the site off the radar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do remember though, this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; secure authentication. You shouldn't rely on this feature for protecting important private data. It's just a simple, shared pass-phrase for very basic privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>&amp;#64;S_Purwadi</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">Sometimes you might want to put your site behind closed doors If you've got a publication that you don't want the world to see yet because it's not ready to launch, you can hide your Ghost site behind a simple shared pass-phrase. You can toggle this preference on at the bottom of Ghost's General Settings Ghost will give you a short, randomly generated pass-phrase which you can share with anyone who needs access to the site while you're working on it. While this setting is enabled, all search engine optimisation features will be switched off to help keep the site off the radar. Do remember though, this is not secure authentication. You shouldn't rely on this feature for protecting important private data. It's just a simple, shared pass-phrase for very basic privacy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Advanced Markdown tips</title><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/advanced-markdown" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advanced Markdown tips" /><published>2017-07-27T05:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T05:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/advanced-markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/advanced-markdown">&lt;p&gt;There are lots of powerful things you can do with the Ghost editor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've gotten pretty comfortable with &lt;a href=&quot;/the-editor/&quot;&gt;all the basics&lt;/a&gt; of writing in Ghost, then you may enjoy some more advanced tips about the types of things you can do with Markdown!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the last post about the editor, you'll want to be actually editing this post as you read it so that you can see all the Markdown code we're using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;specialformatting&quot;&gt;Special formatting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as bold and italics, you can also use some other special formatting in Markdown when the need arises, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;strike through&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;highlight&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;*escaped characters*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;writingcodeblocks&quot;&gt;Writing code blocks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two types of code elements which can be inserted in Markdown, the first is inline, and the other is block. Inline code is formatted by wrapping any word or words in back-ticks, &lt;code&gt;like this&lt;/code&gt;. Larger snippets of code can be displayed across multiple lines using triple back ticks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.my-link {
    text-decoration: underline;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to get really fancy, you can even add syntax highlighting using &lt;a href=&quot;http://prismjs.com/&quot;&gt;Prism.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fullbleedimages&quot;&gt;Full bleed images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One neat trick which you can use in Markdown to distinguish between different types of images is to add a &lt;code&gt;#hash&lt;/code&gt; value to the end of the source URL, and then target images containing the hash with special styling. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://casper.ghost.org/v1.0.0/images/walking.jpg#full&quot; alt=&quot;walking&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is styled with...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;img[src$=&amp;quot;#full&amp;quot;] {
    max-width: 100vw;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates full-bleed images in the Casper theme, which stretch beyond their usual boundaries right up to the edge of the window. Every theme handles these types of things slightly differently, but it's a great trick to play with if you want to have a variety of image sizes and styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;referencelists&quot;&gt;Reference lists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The quick brown &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fox&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia: Fox&quot;&gt;fox&lt;/a&gt;, jumped over the lazy &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dog&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia: Dog&quot;&gt;dog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to insert links in markdown is using reference lists. You might want to use this style of linking to cite reference material in a Wikipedia-style. All of the links are listed at the end of the document, so you can maintain full separation between content and its source or reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;creatingfootnotes&quot;&gt;Creating footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quick brown fox&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; jumped over the lazy dog&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnotes are a great way to add additional contextual details when appropriate. Ghost will automatically add footnote content to the very end of your post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fullhtml&quot;&gt;Full HTML&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the best part of Markdown is that you're never limited to just Markdown. You can write HTML directly in the Ghost editor and it will just work as HTML usually does. No limits! Here's a standard YouTube embed code as an example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cniqsc9QfDo?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;footnotes-sep&quot;&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foxes are red &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dogs are usually not red &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>&amp;#64;S_Purwadi</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">There are lots of powerful things you can do with the Ghost editor If you've gotten pretty comfortable with all the basics of writing in Ghost, then you may enjoy some more advanced tips about the types of things you can do with Markdown! As with the last post about the editor, you'll want to be actually editing this post as you read it so that you can see all the Markdown code we're using. Special formatting As well as bold and italics, you can also use some other special formatting in Markdown when the need arises, for example: strike through highlight *escaped characters* Writing code blocks There are two types of code elements which can be inserted in Markdown, the first is inline, and the other is block. Inline code is formatted by wrapping any word or words in back-ticks, like this. Larger snippets of code can be displayed across multiple lines using triple back ticks: .my-link { text-decoration: underline; } If you want to get really fancy, you can even add syntax highlighting using Prism.js. Full bleed images One neat trick which you can use in Markdown to distinguish between different types of images is to add a #hash value to the end of the source URL, and then target images containing the hash with special styling. For example: which is styled with... img[src$=&amp;quot;#full&amp;quot;] { max-width: 100vw; } This creates full-bleed images in the Casper theme, which stretch beyond their usual boundaries right up to the edge of the window. Every theme handles these types of things slightly differently, but it's a great trick to play with if you want to have a variety of image sizes and styles. Reference lists The quick brown fox, jumped over the lazy dog. Another way to insert links in markdown is using reference lists. You might want to use this style of linking to cite reference material in a Wikipedia-style. All of the links are listed at the end of the document, so you can maintain full separation between content and its source or reference. Creating footnotes The quick brown fox[1] jumped over the lazy dog[2]. Footnotes are a great way to add additional contextual details when appropriate. Ghost will automatically add footnote content to the very end of your post. Full HTML Perhaps the best part of Markdown is that you're never limited to just Markdown. You can write HTML directly in the Ghost editor and it will just work as HTML usually does. No limits! Here's a standard YouTube embed code as an example: Foxes are red ↩︎ Dogs are usually not red ↩︎</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Setting up your own Ghost theme</title><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/themes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Setting up your own Ghost theme" /><published>2017-07-27T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/themes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/themes">&lt;p&gt;Creating a totally custom design for your publication&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghost comes with a beautiful default theme called Casper, which is designed to be a clean, readable publication layout and can be easily adapted for most purposes. However, Ghost can also be completely themed to suit your needs. Rather than just giving you a few basic settings which act as a poor proxy for code, we just let you write code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a huge range of both free and premium pre-built themes which you can get from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://marketplace.ghost.org&quot;&gt;Ghost Theme Marketplace&lt;/a&gt;, or you can simply create your own from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://marketplace.ghost.org&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://casper.ghost.org/v1.0.0/images/marketplace.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;marketplace&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone can write a completely custom Ghost theme, with just some solid knowledge of HTML and CSS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghost themes are written with a templating language called handlebars, which has a bunch of dynamic helpers to insert your data into template files. Like &lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, for example, outputs the name of the current author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to learn how to write your own Ghost theme is to have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/TryGhost/Casper&quot;&gt;the source code for Casper&lt;/a&gt;, which is heavily commented and should give you a sense of how everything fits together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;default.hbs&lt;/code&gt; is the main template file, all contexts will load inside this file unless specifically told to use a different template.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;post.hbs&lt;/code&gt; is the file used in the context of viewing a post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;index.hbs&lt;/code&gt; is the file used in the context of viewing the home page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and so on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've got &lt;a href=&quot;http://themes.ghost.org/docs/about&quot;&gt;full and extensive theme documentation&lt;/a&gt; which outlines every template file, context and helper that you can use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to chat with other people making Ghost themes to get any advice or help, there's also a &lt;strong&gt;#themes&lt;/strong&gt; channel in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://slack.ghost.org&quot;&gt;public Slack community&lt;/a&gt; which we always recommend joining!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>&amp;#64;S_Purwadi</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">Creating a totally custom design for your publication Ghost comes with a beautiful default theme called Casper, which is designed to be a clean, readable publication layout and can be easily adapted for most purposes. However, Ghost can also be completely themed to suit your needs. Rather than just giving you a few basic settings which act as a poor proxy for code, we just let you write code. There are a huge range of both free and premium pre-built themes which you can get from the Ghost Theme Marketplace, or you can simply create your own from scratch. Anyone can write a completely custom Ghost theme, with just some solid knowledge of HTML and CSS Ghost themes are written with a templating language called handlebars, which has a bunch of dynamic helpers to insert your data into template files. Like , for example, outputs the name of the current author. The best way to learn how to write your own Ghost theme is to have a look at the source code for Casper, which is heavily commented and should give you a sense of how everything fits together. default.hbs is the main template file, all contexts will load inside this file unless specifically told to use a different template. post.hbs is the file used in the context of viewing a post. index.hbs is the file used in the context of viewing the home page. and so on We've got full and extensive theme documentation which outlines every template file, context and helper that you can use. If you want to chat with other people making Ghost themes to get any advice or help, there's also a #themes channel in our public Slack community which we always recommend joining!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mumpung Ramadhan</title><link href="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/mumpung-ramadhan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mumpung Ramadhan" /><published>2016-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/mumpung-ramadhan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.purwadi.web.id/v2/mumpung-ramadhan">&lt;p&gt;Sujiwo Tejo seolah menggugat, “Apa enaknya berpuasa bareng-bareng? Aku berpuasa, kau, dan dia, juga mereka, pun kalian, kita semua berpuasa pada hari dan bulan yang sama,” ujarnya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yang Sujiwo Tejo maksud adalah berpuasa di Bulan Suci Ramadhan. Lalu, yang semakin tidak ia mengerti, orang-orang bangun dan makan sahur pada jam-jam yang nyaris serentak. Dan lebih absurd lagi, Tejo bilang, “lalu kita mengadakan acara berbuka puasa bersama.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Aku lebih suka berpuasa seorang diri. Orang-orang tetap makan dan minum, dan aku tidak. Bahkan, ketika itu aku berada di antara mereka. Ini puasa yang asyik,” kata dalang yang juga pemain saksofon dan komposer itu, dalam majelis Suluk Maleman di Rumah Adab Mulia Indonesia, di Pati, Jawa Tengah, 13 Juni malam lalu. Baginya, dan bagi orang-orang yang merasakan hal yang sama, Bulan Suci Ramadhan justru menjelma bulan makan-minum teratur. Bulan konsumtif, bulan ketika grafik inflasi meningkat hingga lebaran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sujiwo Tejo yang ke mana-mana kini suka melantangkan lantunan ayat-ayat suci Al Qur’an di luar pakem Qira’atul Sab’ah ini lebih suka jika bahkan tidak ada yang tahu dirinya sedang berpuasa. Atau berpuasa dengan godaan yang komplit: aneka santapan boleh tetap di meja makan, warung-warung leluasa buka, kehidupan malam dibiarkan apa adanya, dan orang-orang tak perlu tiba-tiba berakting diri mereka beriman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tidak hanya itu. Sujiwo Tejo menaruh kecurigaan: jangan-jangan berpuasa di luar Ramadhan lebih baik dari berpuasa di Bulan Suci yang penuh berkah ini. Ya, Allah memang berjanji akan memberi rahmat pada sepuluh hari pertama, ampunan pada sepuluh hari kedua, dan perlindungan dari api neraka pada sepuluh hari ketiga. Belum termasuk anugerah Lailatul Qadar yang bahkan nilainya lebih baik dari seribu bulan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sujiwo Tejo, yang musikus dan penulis itu, memang terbiasa dengan ritme. Tak ayal, ia menduga Bulan Suci Ramadhan semacam interval atau spasi atau jeda dari sebelas bulan lainnya dalam satu tahun berjalan. Tapi, pandangannya itu sesungguhnya segendang-seperiangan dengan petuah para kiai. Yakni jadikan ibadah di Bulan Suci Ramadhan serupa latihan yang keras sebelum kita benar-benar berlaga sebelas bulan ke depan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;in&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Mindset yg dibentuk oleh iklan2 penyehat/penguat org puasa: Puasa itu masalah, hrs dibantu obat2an…Padahal puasa itu MENYEHATKAN. Halo KPI&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Reklamasi Jancukers (@sudjiwotedjo) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sudjiwotedjo/status/606795492660412416&quot;&gt;June 5, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Namun, apa jadinya jika orang-orang yang berpuasa di Bulan Suci Ramadhan menuntut untuk dihormati oleh orang-orang yang tidak berpuasa? Sebelas bulan ke depan, apa jadinya jika giliran mereka yang tidak berpuasa? Akankah mereka menghormati orang lain yang berpuasa? Ataukah egosentris ini cuma di Bulan Suci Ramadhan? Bukankah saling menghormati lebih baik daripada saling tidak menghormati?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;in&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Akan lbh dalem bila yg puasa mengucap &amp;quot;hormatilah yg tak puasa&amp;quot;, sedang yg tak puasa mengucap &amp;quot;Hormatilah yg puasa&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Reklamasi Jancukers (@sudjiwotedjo) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sudjiwotedjo/status/608596852301123584&quot;&gt;June 10, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tentu, tema obrolan meluas jika lantas mulai membanding-bandingkan. Hari Raya Nyepi di Bali, misalnya, berlaku secara umum bagi siapa pun. Tak hanya umat Hindu, siapa pun yang pada hari itu berada di Pulau Dewata diwajibkan untuk patigeni atau tidak menyalakan pelita. Bali gelap gulita. Bahkan bandar udara internasional Ngurah Rai sampai ditutup. Tapi hanya sehari, bayangkan jika itu berlangsung satu bulan penuh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bayangkan jika warung, resto, kafe, dan tempat makan-minum lainnya, serta toko-toko sembako, ditutup total satu bulan penuh. Bayangkan Bulan Suci Ramadhan benar-benar menjelma bulan untuk merasakan lapar dan dahaga. Kita makan-minum seadanya. Bukan justru jadwal makan menjadi teratur, menu menjadi lengkap, dan yang tidak ada pada sebelas bulan lainnya menjadi harus ada di Bulan Suci Ramadhan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jika berpuasa Ramadhan dimaknai sebagai menahan lapar dan haus, maka kita akan memperlihatkan wujud asli setelah adzan maghrib berkumandang. Kita melahap apa pun demi membayar rasa lapar dan haus seharian. Semacam balas dendam. Bulan Suci Ramadhan menjelma sebagai bulan aji mumpung. Mumpung Ramadhan, ini harus ada, itu harus tersedia. Toh cuma sebulan dalam setahun. Tidak sepanjang tahun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berpuasa seharusnya lebih tentang menahan makan-minum tentu juga menahan hawa nafsu lain, termasuk hubungan badan suami-istri. Bukan menahan lapar dan dahaga. Sebab, kita justru diminta merasakan lapar dahaga yang dialami fakir miskin dan anak yatim piatu. Jika tidak begitu, wajar jika tingkat konsumsi justru naik bahkan paling tinggi dalam setahun di bulan yang semestinya paling hemat ini.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bulan Suci Ramadhan juga bukan cuma mengenai kewajiban berpuasa. Banyak sunnah lainnya. Dua di antaranya ialah sahur dan berbuka puasa. Maka, tidak perlu mencemooh mereka yang masih sebatas ikut-ikutan sahur dan berbuka puasa. Tidak/ belum mendapat pahala dari ibadah wajib, setidaknya mendapat pahala melalui ibadah sunnah. Semoga Allah kemudian memberinya hidayah dan kekuatan untuk berpuasa penuh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alangkah indah jika kita jadikan Bulan Suci Ramadhan sebagai bulan bahagia. Akur, rukun, damai. Tidak memaksakan kehendak antara yang satu dan yang lain. Tidak memaki, tidak pula merusak. Tidak merazia, tidak pula menghardik. Dalam Hadits Qudsi, dari Abu Hurairah RA, Rasulullah SAW bersabda,”Puasa itu perisai. Jika sedang berpuasa, jangan kalian mengucapkan kata-kata kotor dan jangan pula berbuat bodoh.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masih dalam hadits yang diriwayatkan Bukhari itu, diserukan,”Jika ada yang mencela dan mengganggu, ucapkan: saya sedang berpuasa.” Kalimatnya sungguh jelas, yaitu: “Saya sedang berpuasa.” Tidak perlu kita tambah-tambahi menjadi kalimat baru, yaitu: “Hormati saya yang sedang berpuasa.” Sebab, puasa bukanlah untuk mencari penghormatan dari sesama manusia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terlebih, dalam Hadits Qudsi lainnya yang juga diriwayatkan oleh Bukhari, dari Abu Hurairah RA, Rasulullah SAW bersabda,”Seluruh amal anak Adam adalah untuknya sendiri, kecuali puasa. Sesungguhnya, puasa itu untukKu dan Aku akan membalasnya.” Jadi, puasa wajib di Bulan Suci Ramadhan maupun puasa sunnah di sebelas bulan lainnya, tidak perlu menjadikan kita merasa lebih benar dan suci dari orang lain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;in&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Ditanya, &amp;quot;Kamu shalat ndak? Zakat ndak?&amp;quot; aku masih bisa paham. Kalau ditanya &amp;quot;Puasa ndak?&amp;quot; Bingung. Krn Puasa urusannya langsung ma Tuhan&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Reklamasi Jancukers (@sudjiwotedjo) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sudjiwotedjo/status/489156748595322881&quot;&gt;July 15, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oleh Candra Malik (praktisi Tasawuf yang bergiat di bidang kesusastraan, kesenian, dan kebudayaan.)
Dipublikasikan di Koran Tempo edisi 18 Juni 2015&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>&amp;#64;S_Purwadi</name></author><category term="Islam" /><summary type="html">Sujiwo Tejo seolah menggugat, “Apa enaknya berpuasa bareng-bareng? Aku berpuasa, kau, dan dia, juga mereka, pun kalian, kita semua berpuasa pada hari dan bulan yang sama,” ujarnya.</summary></entry></feed>